<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Thebstar</title>
    <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs" />
    <updated>2024-09-15T02:14:28+05:30</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bikram</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Life is Good</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/life-is-good.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/life-is-good.html</id>

        <updated>2024-09-15T02:14:28+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This is September 15th 2024, IST 2:05am. I am at Mumbai airport. Waiting for my fight to home. Boarding will start at 2.30. So I have like 20 minutes to write it. So, I will make it short. Let's just talk about why am I&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>This is September 15th 2024, IST 2:05am. I am at Mumbai airport. Waiting for my fight to home. Boarding will start at 2.30. So I have like 20 minutes to write it. So, I will make it short. Let's just talk about why am I writting this. </p>
<p>Life has been good to me. Things had started to fall into right places. Mentally, Physically, Financially. Whenever I didn't feel like it, I tried and tried to put them in the right places. I tried to make the life good. And now, since it has been good, averaging really good for sometime, I feel this is the right time to unleash the bull run. Take the average higher. This is important to do when I am in control. We never know when life flips it and starts a bear run. </p>
<p>I am brining this blog back from ashes for the bull run, for the higher average. It is not only an opportunity but a responsibility now to make this run. This blog will act as the brain dump yard, accountability partner no one asked.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Cheers. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
