<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Thebstar blogs</title>
    <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs" />
    <updated>2024-09-23T10:07:26+05:30</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bikram</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Personal website is live 🚀</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/personal-website-is-live.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/personal-website-is-live.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/7/Screenshot-2024-09-23-at-12.39.41-AM.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="life"/>

        <updated>2024-09-23T00:39:12+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/7/Screenshot-2024-09-23-at-12.39.41-AM.png" alt="Bikram&#x27;s website" />
                    Okay, it was live always, but wasn't updated. My website and blogs were in one place. To write a blog I had to open my terminal and a code editor. This was a huge friction. And slowly as I mentioned earlier, Whatsapp notes took over.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/7/Screenshot-2024-09-23-at-12.39.41-AM.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Bikram&#x27;s website" /></p>
                <p>Okay, it was live always, but wasn't updated. My website and blogs were in one place. To write a blog I had to open my terminal and a code editor. This was a huge friction. And slowly as I mentioned earlier, Whatsapp notes took over. I started taking notes on Apple notes, Whatsapp self-DM, and on my iPad.</p>
<p>Updating the website and blog was always in my mind. So much that, I started building a blog engine. Visual blog builder. It worked. It can create basic page with a visual rich text editor. <a href="https://github.com/theBstar/blogder" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Still a prototype - find it on github here</a>. As I started using it, I found it needs a lot of features. Initially plan was to just build the features. But I have limited time. And I wanted to build a blog engine to just start blogging again. I wanted to build it, such that I didn't have to open my terminal and IDE to dump something. Fortunately, <a href="https://getpublii.com/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer">I found Publii, a public open-source static CMS</a>. It does exactly this. I can write without touching terminal, IDE, without thinking deployment, and it connects to github pages. YaY 🥳 !</p>
<p>I am back at writing online. It is fun again. Now, I had to update the homepage. <a href="https://v0.dev/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">V0.dev</a> has been one of the best things on frontend in recent times. I coded up the initial page with just a few touches. And <a href="https://www.thebstar.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the updated website is also live - same old url thebstar.com.</a> 🚀</p>
<p>I have picked up a really good pace in the last 2 weeks. This blog is just the tip of it. Just a sneak peek into my builder energy picking up. Will be sharing more soon!</p>
<p>Cool, lets do some small talk. I went shirt-less twice in a crowd last week. I was attending a funeral of a friend's dad. Last rituals were on the bank of a river. We took a bath afterwards. Later in the week, I went to singri to do nets practice on Saturday (21st September 2024). Went shirt-less again due to heat and sweat. I have some fotage from the session, and I look good. I hadn't seen some of those muscles (I still have to look hard though 😅). Motivation to hit the gym. 💪 I have missed the gym for last 3 weeks completely. Had to do some travel. Will tell the story later. This is already long and it is almost 1am now. </p>
<p>Take care!</p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Self Note - Present is real!</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/self-note-present-is-real.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/self-note-present-is-real.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/4/download.jpeg" medium="image" />
            <category term="fokat"/>

        <updated>2024-09-17T00:12:46+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/4/download.jpeg" alt="" />
                    Past is gone. Future is yet to come. Present is what you live. It is easy to carry burden of past and bias our decisions - Morgan Housel, The Psychology of Money. Similarly it is easier to look too much into future and ruin our&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/4/download.jpeg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>Past is gone. Future is yet to come. Present is what you live. It is easy to carry burden of past and bias our decisions - Morgan Housel, The Psychology of Money. Similarly it is easier to look too much into future and ruin our present. </p>
<p>Present, now is the <span style="text-decoration: line-through;">most valuable</span> resource to get to future. It is the only resource. It is the only oil. Important to realise, every moment you spend thinking, or doing something is burning this most important fuel. Is future that important to be considered now? Do I need to go that deeper into future? Is it worth my present?</p>
<p>But life isn't this linear, nor everything has equal weight. Some things even in distant future have greater importance in life. Some experiences from past carry bigger lessons than others. So, we have to aware of the weights. And if it comes down to optimising for past, present or future. It should be always between present and future. <strong>And importance in future should have higher relative weights as closer they are in the timeline</strong>. This is importnat because, time is moving in one direction, so is life, and the best part of the life. But don't forget to enjoy the current moment. I will expand on it. Let it be meta for now. Let the entirety of this be meta for now.</p>
<p>I was coming back from Mumbai. Bus journey took 8 hours instead of usual 5. I had planned take an hour long nap in the afternoon. But I reached at 4pm. I had a play rehearsal scheduled at 6pm. I had almost slotted a nap after reaching home. So, I was feeling sleepy. But I couldn't sleep for and hour, wake up do the preparation and go to the play rehearsal. This wasn't possible. So, I decided to put some work. And later wrote this down. Went to rehearsal at 6. </p>
<p>I am coming back to this and publishing it. With the updated title. Yes, Present is real. I should be optimising it, without blocking myself on past excuses, experiences. And I start to embrace more chaos in life, being able to open myself to frequent changes in plan, schedule, optimising for present is the best thing I can do for better use of the fuel. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Life is Good</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/life-is-good.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/life-is-good.html</id>
            <category term="life"/>
            <category term="fokat"/>

        <updated>2024-09-15T02:14:28+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    This is September 15th 2024, IST 2:05am. I am at Mumbai airport. Waiting for my fight to home. Boarding will start at 2.30. So I have like 20 minutes to write it. So, I will make it short. Let's just talk about why am I&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>This is September 15th 2024, IST 2:05am. I am at Mumbai airport. Waiting for my fight to home. Boarding will start at 2.30. So I have like 20 minutes to write it. So, I will make it short. Let's just talk about why am I writting this. </p>
<p>Life has been good to me. Things had started to fall into right places. Mentally, Physically, Financially. Whenever I didn't feel like it, I tried and tried to put them in the right places. I tried to make the life good. And now, since it has been good, averaging really good for sometime, I feel this is the right time to unleash the bull run. Take the average higher. This is important to do when I am in control. We never know when life flips it and starts a bear run. </p>
<p>I am brining this blog back from ashes for the bull run, for the higher average. It is not only an opportunity but a responsibility now to make this run. This blog will act as the brain dump yard, accountability partner no one asked.</p>
<p> </p>
<p>Cheers. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
