<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Thebstar blogs</title>
    <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs" />
    <updated>2025-09-27T23:47:15+05:30</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Self aware - we all are, aren&#x27;t we!Â </title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/self-aware-we-all-are-arent-we.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/self-aware-we-all-are-arent-we.html</id>

        <updated>2025-09-25T02:17:00+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    11:53 PM, Wednesday, September 2025, I am writing this after a reflective conversation with a friend. Emotional intelligence, self-awareness, all this jargon gets thrown around a lot these days. What are they really? And why should you care? And who am I to write about&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>11:53 PM, Wednesday, September 2025, I am writing this after a reflective conversation with a friend. Emotional intelligence, self-awareness, all this jargon gets thrown around a lot these days. What are they really? And why should you care? And who am I to write about these? And why should you read this?</p>
<p>Let me start with the last question: why should you read this? Everyone gets a $20 Amazon voucher at the end. Kidding. <strong>I will give you simple steps to have magical connections with people</strong>. If people tell/complain to you about the following, you should read -</p>
<ul>
<li>You aren't aware - self-aware, emotionally aware, socially aware, etc.</li>
<li>You don't listen to me</li>
<li>You don't get me</li>
<li>You don't tell me, you don't open up, I don't understand you</li>
<li>You don't ask me questions</li>
<li>You don't have time for me</li>
<li>I can't trust you, I don't believe you</li>
<li>And so on.Â </li>
</ul>
<p>Let's start with who am I? I am rated decently on the EQ scale, based on the people I have had interactions with, and they are highly rated for their EQ in the social circle. These are mostly successful founders or executives in the tech world. I am also connected to random strangers, listening to their life stories and sharing some of mine. I can't stop; there is another jargon I can throw here. But let me save that for later, this article anyway is gonna be long, hence no digression or twist.Â </p>
<p>I said no twist, hence let me make the context very clear upfront. Or you won't trust me, right? ðŸ˜„.Â </p>
<ol>
<li>If you had asked any of the above people about my EQ, let's say 15 years ago, they would have rated me very pathetically.Â Â </li>
<li>Interestingly, I would have still rated myself very high.Â </li>
</ol>
<p>To make it easier to understand both 1 &amp; 2, let me define what EQ and/or self-awareness really are. I don't follow textbooks; please bear with me.Â </p>
<h3>Self awareness</h3>
<p>Let's start with this. Let's start very simply. Every living thing that knows of its existence is self-aware. It is a very broad definition. For this conversation, let's stick to Humans. Every mentally healthy human being is self-aware. We know - we exist, we know we are hungry, we know we are angry, <strong>we know we are seen, heard, we are loved</strong>.Â </p>
<p>There is more depth to it, but trust me, you don't need to know them yet. They will just complicate things for you. Let's roll for now -</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Every mentally healthy human being is self-aware. We know - we exist, we know we are hungry, we know we are angry, <strong>we know we are seen, heard, we are loved</strong>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>We know we are self-aware, but maybe we don't know the way to express this. Or why do we even need to express it?</p>
<h3>EQ (Emotional Intelligence)</h3>
<p>Well, EQ is the more quantifiable version of emotional intelligence, easy for comparisons. We humans love comparisons. I will use 'EQ' because it is short &amp; easy. Tell me already, what is it?</p>
<p>Did you notice something in bold in the last paragraph? "<strong>We know we are seen, heard, we are loved."Â </strong>- These are the most fundamental needs of us, the humans. And this is what makes us human. We want to be seen, we want to be heard, and we want to be loved. And <strong>EQ is nothing but how much you can make someone feel seen, heard, and loved. </strong>This is why we need to express. I will make them feel that my act is so naive, because we can't always act (in the cliche "act" definition), or we can, actually making them feel is an act. Making ourselves feel is an act.Â </p>
<blockquote>
<p>EQ is how much you can make someone feel seen, heard, and loved.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Don't come looking for my address to beat me up. I am gonna share more definitions. What does it mean to be seen, heard, and loved? If people feel seen, heard, and loved, all the above questions will be resolved correctly. I assure you, most of them would be gone.Â </p>
<h3>People want to be seen</h3>
<p>People want to be seen. They want you to notice them. We humans are so expressive. Even the most poker-faced people, even the most introverted people, want to be seen. You can't disagree. Please don't. Or how else would you explain walking up late, not having a good sleep, or having less energy on bad days? How would you explain your tone changing in conversations? How would you explain your leaning to people? And what about your eyes - pupils? We want to express. We are storytellers. And we want to be seen.Â </p>
<p>We want people to notice, notice the phases we are going through. Notice the bad day we are having. Notice the new dress we got. Those restaurants, family shops want you to notice their great-grandparents, who would have the pictures of them hanging on the main wall.Â </p>
<p>Or why else did we put Mahatma Gandhi's picture in the note? Why do we give people Bharat Ranta or the Nobel Prize?</p>
<p>We want ot be seen. Ask honestly, ask with an empty mind - imagine one fine morning you woke up, had a really good day. You are all happy and in a good mood (because your body wants to be seen). You want to tell it to someone. And your loved ones, family, ask, "You look so happy today".Â </p>
<p>We want others to notice this. Down shoulders, energy level, tone, mood - if you want to call it. How we react, how we act. We want others to see our emotions. <strong>But why?</strong></p>
<h3>Why do we want to be seen? We want to be heard</h3>
<p>Yes, we want to be seen, because we want to be heard. We are storytellers. Evolved over a thousand years in close setup, in groups, and civilizations. We want to be relatable, we want to be listened to, we want to feel understood, we want people to empathize, we want to share happiness, we want to find hope...</p>
<p>If being seen is important, it is 10x more important to be heard. We can walk alone in a crowd, knowing no one will see us; we just need one person who makes us feel we are heard. Isn't it better to have a lot of people who make us feel seen, heard, and we do the same for them? If all of these relate, do share this with your friend. Maybe this is the only article that is written on my blog for sharing.Â </p>
<p>We want to be heard because it makes us feel we are not alone; we are part of something. And when I say "heard", I mean understanding me. We want to feel understood. And act if/what is possible in their capacity. It isn't always possible to act.Â </p>
<p>Have you seen a baby cry? Infants, when they start growing up, close to 8/9 months, they start identifying objects. But they still don't understand that things can exist outside of their vision.Â  They cry, not seeing Momy, because they don't yet have the perception that Momy can exist even when she isn't in their sight. And when they see mommy, they want to go to her, because she knows them. She understands her crying. They don't have a language, but they still express, they still want to be seen. And they feel so good, because they feel heard. <a href="https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC5330336/" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer">Success, happiness in the later part of life is so much connected with how deep their bonds are, how much they had to cry before someone cared for them.Â </a></p>
<h3>Isn't this love? We want to feel loved</h3>
<p>We want to feel seen, heard, trusted, respected, and cared for. If we get these, this is what love is. The mixture will look different in different stages of life. But you know all of these just compound over time. And if we practice seeing, hearing, and with respect, trust, and a bit of action and care, love is the beautiful result. It isn't magic. If this mixture doesn't fit well, if any of these vectors are disrupted repeatedly, the feeling of love will start to fade. It is one thing to feel loved; it is another to make someone feel loved. Both are magical, out of this world. I can talk about consciousness and out-of-the-world feeling more. But you would already be yelling at me. Hence, let me give you easy tricks to practice seeing and hearing.Â </p>
<h3>Last stop before the destination, Communication is a multi-step funnel</h3>
<p>Please bear with me for a few minutes, and I will hand you the tricks. It is important to understand that communication is a multi-step process. And in each step, there is a huge drop-off involved. Have you been to any public events? You see 100 people attending the event initially, and by the closing ceremony, there would just be say 40/50 people. And when you are in the organising committee, and you have to clean up the mess, it is just those handful of people. How hard is it to keep all those people in the event till you clean up the place and everyone walks out together? Pretty hard, right? Communication is equally hard. Don't laugh at me. I might be sounding silly. All of us have been communicating since birth, haven't found it hard. Barely any inconvenience, right? Let's set this up.</p>
<ol>
<li>You want to say something</li>
<li>You say something</li>
<li>The other person listens to something</li>
<li>They understand something</li>
</ol>
<p>1, 2, 3, 4 can all be different.Â </p>
<p>You might want to say something, but can't frame it well, can't recall the exact word. So there is a difference between 1 &amp; 2 already. And this is just you.Â </p>
<p>Another person might miss a few words, an external disturbance, or their mental state. And they might make a different meaning out of it. Because they are a different person and they have lived different experiences in a different environment. What they listen to and what they understand can look so different. By this time, what you want to say might have come across as something different to this other person.Â </p>
<p>This can happen to us as well; what we listen to might be so different than what other people are actually trying to say.Â </p>
<p>How do we communicate better, so there is less room for errors? How do we ensure there is minimal drop off? Here we go, the tricks -</p>
<ol>
<li>Don't assume anything. If you have any assumptions, lay them clearly. We don't know others' situations, others' lives, and our assumptions will always be incomplete if not wrong.Â 
<ul>
<li>Ask questions. If you have assumptions, ask if that assumption is correct.Â </li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Listen carefully, give them enough space to talk
<ul>
<li>Again, ask questions, but don't just listen to ask questions. Let your curiosity be your guide. There are no stupid questions.</li>
<li>If you feel like something stupid, personal, say it out loud to people. E.g., this might sound stupid, but I have this thing. And make them comfortable ignoring the thought/question. This will make your life easier, and their life easier if they want to ignore.Â </li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Make sure you understand
<ul>
<li>Ask clarifying questions. Something like "..., is this correct, am I understanding this alright?"</li>
<li>Summarize to them their own statements.Â </li>
<li>If needed, ask for more information,</li>
<li>Don't assume, ask questions, ask questions</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Understand their need
<ul>
<li>Are they asking a question?Â </li>
<li>Why are they asking?Â </li>
<li>You aren't writing an exam. You aren't given an MCQ.Â </li>
<li>Ask questions. Answer their questions</li>
<li><strong>Avoid 1 line replies as much as possible</strong>.Â </li>
<li>Give context, tell stories, we are storytellers.Â </li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Now it is time to give back
<ul>
<li>Make sure you are understoodÂ 
<ul>
<li>Set the context, set the theme, set intentions - with very clear words</li>
<li>Ask clarifying questions</li>
<li>Repeat main lines</li>
<li>Don't give a very long monologue, like this article. ðŸ˜…</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>To be understood, give them space to ask questions, give them space to carry on conversations
<ul>
<li><strong>It is important for you to feel understood; it is equally important for your close ones to feel, they understand you. Or, they would be kicking themselves every day.Â </strong></li>
<li>For the dumbest question like - Hey, did you eat something?
<ul>
<li>Think why are they asking? Why are they making fool of them? What would they do with the information?</li>
<li>Well, because they care. They want to make you feel seen and heard.</li>
<li>Some answers to the question
<ul>
<li>Yes.</li>
<li>Yes, just ate xy.</li>
<li>Yes, had xy. Went out to eat after so many days. It was too hot and I didn't feel like getting out of my ac cabin. But I had to see the sun right. I don't regret going out now. Although traffic was bad. But I saw a few kids walking back from school all jumping around. So happy faces.Â </li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>You know, to anwer like the last anwer you have to see things, notice them, hear them. Trust me you will live more joyfully.Â </li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>If you aren't heard,Â 
<ul>
<li>Remind them, Give them reasons
<ul>
<li>Let's say you have to get your book back, you had asked them already. Being heard means, being understood. If they didn't do their act, itis time to remind
<ul>
<li>Hey, send my book back
<ul>
<li>Sounds like you don't trust them.Â </li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Hey, send me the book back? Its been a while so I thought of reminding you.Â 
<ul>
<li>I kept the first sentence same, intentionally. I added the reason and they now know why I am needing to remind.Â </li>
<li>They can reply with something like - I was really busy shifting my house. I am still finding where have I kept it.</li>
<li>You didn't know, they were shifiting house, be curious, ask where, when did they shift, and if you feel comformtable (why not) ask why did they shift?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Open up, Share your volunaribilitiesÂ 
<ul>
<li>Share how you are also struggling with current landlord.Â </li>
<li>This might be an oppotunity find a new house, or a chance to just relate and being heard.Â </li>
<li>Sharing volunaribilities doesn't make you weak, instead it makes the connections stronger. People can relate to you more, and they can trust you more.Â </li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Practice above for a few days actively. Reflect on your conversations and think where you could have given more context, where you could have made others feel more understood. Where you felt seen, heard, loved.Â </li>
</ol>
<h3>Easy self awareness</h3>
<p>When you feel seen, heard, loved - I want you to ask yourself what made you feel that.Â </p>
<p>Let's tryÂ </p>
<p>I felt loved today. Why? Because I met Y. Why? Why did meeting Y made me feel loved? Because Y loves me, cares me? Those are abstract things, I want specific answers, How does Y make me feel loved? Y was so excited to meet me, I felt special. <strong>Well we are somewhere</strong>.</p>
<p>It is such a good feeling. I want Y to feel this. But hey, did I make Y feel the same?Â Â </p>
<ul>
<li>If Yes - well done! Let me tell Y, if I can, I feel so good now.Â </li>
<li>If no - I still have time, Let me tell Y, I felt so good after the meeting. And let me try to make the feeling same for Y from next time.Â </li>
</ul>
<p>We are truly self aware now. We don't only know our emotions and states, but we also recognise the triggers. Why it happened in the first place. And we are doing so good with the social, relationship EQ, by relaying this. And making others live lovely.Â </p>
<p>I want you to try this for next few days, whenever you sit to eat something -</p>
<ol>
<li>I want you to ask - How do I feel now? Why do why I feel so? And follow the above template.
<ul>
<li>What can I do better right now, to feel seen, heard and loved?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I want you to ask who is the most important person I met so far today, How did I make them feel?Â 
<ul>
<li>Did I make them feel seen, heard, loved?</li>
<li>If not what can I do now?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Â </p>
<h3>Let me summarize, just the tricks</h3>
<p>To be self aware and rank high on EQ we need feel to be seen, heard and loved. And we need to make others feel seen, heard and loved. We don't need to complicate the world. We need to practice active, no-stupic open communication. We need to constantly listening ot our own feelings, by asking right questions. We need to be listenings others to understand them as much.</p>
<p><strong>Let me give you two simple tricksÂ </strong></p>
<p>First, I want you do follow this while sitting to eat, 3 time a day, like a medicine for next 1 week.Â </p>
<ol>
<li>I want you to ask - How do I feel now? Why do why I feel so? And follow the above template.
<ul>
<li>What can I do better right now, to feel seen, heard and loved?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>I want you to ask who is the most important person I met so far today, How did I make them feel?Â 
<ul>
<li>Did I make them feel seen, heard, loved?</li>
<li>If not what can I do now?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>
<p>2nd, everyday at night I want you to re-read the 6 communication steps. Keep a counter of how many times you try something from the steps without thinking much in next 1 week.Â </p>
<p>Â </p>
<p>I want you to re-read this article tomorrow once - just do a brief walk. <strong>Comeback and re-read this article after a week.Â </strong></p>
<p>We are storytellers. Self aware, we all are. I want you to feel seen, heard and loved. Take care.Â </p>
<p>Â </p>
<p>Â </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>I recorded a video</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/i-recorded-a-video.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/i-recorded-a-video.html</id>

        <updated>2025-09-24T17:10:58+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    24th September I attended a practice session yesterday and recorded a video of myself. Well, I do record myself practicing, but this was more like a monologue on the way. I have been thinking of recording my thoughts and sharing some of my stories, along&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p><strong>24th September</strong></p>
<p>I attended a practice session yesterday and recorded a video of myself. Well, I do record myself practicing, but this was more like a monologue on the way.Â </p>
<p>I have been thinking of recording my thoughts and sharing some of my stories, along with visuals, for some time. A, for my own reference, and b, for people close to me to watch them. And I wanted to buy a 360 camera for some time, it just seems like the friction to record is so low with them. This happens to be the sale season on both Amazon and Flipkart, and the camera is 11k discounted with a card discount. Maybe it is the signal to buy.Â </p>
<p>I want to buy it and record myself, yeah, these long monologues. But I also worry about exposing my thoughts to more people. Text requires so much effort to read; in contrast, videos require little effort. I am not very natural with word selections in Assamese or Nepali; I don't know if I shall record in Hindi. The fact that I have been doing journaling in English over the years, it is the language of my thoughts. And my parents won't understand English. Defeats the purpose of recording myself. I can switch to other languages, but recording is a great way to improve/practice this ad hoc thought structuring. I want to do this in English. It isn't for people to watch. It is for myself. And for parents, oh, they get to see me, and I will say a few words to them, and add explanation when required.Â </p>
<p>To be continued...</p>
<p><strong>27th September</strong></p>
<p>Sounds like I am overthinking this. But hey, I have already recorded a video. No way I am overthinking. It shouldn't really matter who would understand and watch these. I shall just record. In whatever language I feel. If it is a self-talk monologue, surely it is going to be in English, or if I feel I will talk Assamese or Nepali. If I get asked by people, I will think about language. If I have a situation, the situation should dictate the language. However, I don't think I will record a situation. I think I am confused. Let's reframe the question.Â </p>
<p>Why do I want to record?Â To structure my thoughts, practice the flow. Really? Maybe not.Â </p>
<p>I want to record the video to share my thoughts, to answer my worries about recording. And while doing so, practice my flow. Can I do both? I can't.Â </p>
<p>If I am recording my monologue, I don't need an extra camera, I don't need to think story. I could be sharing anything. And I can expect the audience will have some idea of what I am saying. I should still write. And my flow practice is done as well. But how can I omit my parents, who will click on the link to watch and not understand anything?Â </p>
<p>This is the reason I haven't been able to share or record a 2nd one. Anyway. I will record and see how it goes. Probably I will not record that much as well, not worth thinking about this complexity.</p>
<p>I shall revisit after recording 10th. Let's go âš¡</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Is this 2020?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/is-this-2020.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/is-this-2020.html</id>

        <updated>2025-09-13T08:14:02+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    Is this 2020? Because I am back. I am back as the beast. I am a beast. I want to say this so much - I have sold my soul back to the devil. It is somewhat of a known phrase. Somehow, I came up&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Is this 2020? Because I am back. I am back as the beast. I am a beast.Â </p>
<p>I want to say this so much - <strong>I have sold my soul back to the devil</strong>. It is somewhat of a known phrase. Somehow, I came up with it, and I had been using it for a few years until I discovered GPT and asked it. Yes, I had sold my soul to the devil, maybe from 2017 to 2019. Then something happened in 2019.Â </p>
<p>My family, a big group of 13 people, was visiting Bangalore. For a ritual retreat. The plan was to spend 20 days there, visiting temples and a few other places. We did the trip, and COVID happened. Everything was stopped. <strong>They ended up spending 2 months</strong>. I was working from home. It was a 1BHK. I had gotten used to staying alone, even in physical presence; I had learnt to do that. I was out and away from 2011. I was never a social person from the inside. Even now (maybe we will come to this).</p>
<p>Now the backstory is set, let's come back. Why do I have to start with a backstory? Almost every 2nd story of mine starts with a backstory. ðŸ˜…. When I say I had sold my soul to the devil, I meant to say I was so within myself, with myself, and so dedicated to what I was doing, and wanted to do it so well, as if I were fighting a battle, I wouldn't have been able to take rest even after conquering the entire world. At that point, I wasn't about the results. It was the fight, the pain, the suffering -<strong> that's what the devil offered</strong>, and the fun of it was what I loved the most. I went places. I re-found the best of my fighting abilities. But I lost connections in return, not that I ever missed.Â </p>
<p>In 2019, COVID times freed my soul from the devil. I wanted to come back home, be with my parents and my siblings. I had stayed away from them for so long. I broke the pact. I got my soul back. I thought there was no payback. I wasn't losing something. Now, I look back at things in 2025, and I had looked back in 2024. I did lose the "forever on" beast mode. I still go back to the shadows, but that beast, He was so good, so relentless. I miss that consistency.Â </p>
<p>Did the devil take its power away? Or were the powers always within me? It is good that I made the pact and realised <strong>my powers</strong>. My powers, within me. No, the Devil never gave me those; those powers were mine always. My soul can be out in the world, and I can still be the best. I am a beast who has a fire within, but calm and as peaceful as it can look. My mom used to say, Look at the sea, it looks so calm, but within it holds so much power. She realized it doesn't look that calm when she saw the sea ðŸ˜…. Be the sea, powerful, tsunami inside, calm, soothing outside. And if I am that, without me needing to be, why not? - And how can I end a story without giving my Mom references? Let me tell you, this isn't a story, and this isn't ending here. Let's move to the next paragraph, shall we?</p>
<p>It feels like 2020, I had gotten back my soul, but I was still a beast. Took 2021, 2022 easily. 2022 very lazily, took me 2023 just recovering. 2024 was so much uncertainty. I could have done better in 2022, even with the rest. But I had reasons, and choices. I can't judge myself now, since things have gone well. 2025 feels so much like 2020. I have started to feel the pump, I have started to wake up and do morning runs. âš¡ âš¡</p>
<p>Lately, I have come to a realization: pay me a leadership course fee if you want ðŸ˜…. Good leaders make things very clear. They say I am gonna change the world, but they don't just stop there. Changing the world is so ambitious; it can mean so many things. So they go ahead and define what it is. They go ahead and define actions that can lead us there. I say a lot of these abstract, meta, ambitious statements. In the last two months, I have started practicing breaking them into reality, small actions, and I have been seeing results. I had realised this, and a conversation with Divyansh really helped. Thanks to him. At work, in life, I have been practicing them everywhere. I am no self-help expert; before I write an entire article on this, this needs maturing in my mind. I didn't promise it, so if it is found useful, it is the prize of sticking along. There should always be a prize, and there is always.Â </p>
<p><strong>Example</strong></p>
<p>Previous me -Â  You should lead people. You should lead a team. (You also want it, and why/how it will help you). - I would usually leave the "how" part of leading, or doing anything. I used to leave it blank for people to figure out.Â </p>
<p>How I say this now - You should lead people. And there are opportunities to do the same. Do x with y. It will help both of you for "this" reason. And there are another 5 gaps I can see clearly you can fill in. What do you think? (Listen &amp; narrow down). Great, let's try this one or these 2 things then. (It is their idea now. Instead of leaving them with a blank page, I started giving them fill-in-the-blank and let them take care of the most important gaps.Â </p>
<p>***</p>
<p>Since I just spoke about this new framework, what does it mean to be a beast in action? What does it mean to be a best and still not sell the soul to the devil? Maybe, now, <strong>I have sold my soul to the brightest of the light, or calmest of the Infinity there is</strong>.Â </p>
<p>Â </p>
<p><strong>Beast</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Someone who does all of his actions without thinking even for a second.Â </li>
<li>He isn't motivated; he doesn't need it. If anything, he inspires himself.Â </li>
<li>He does all this just for the sake of doing it. He does get fun out of it, but he doesn't even care about the fun. For him, it is a relentless pursuit of the fight that feels eternal, that he feels like fighting for eternity.Â Â </li>
<li>People stare into his eyes and might feel restless, but kids would still be inspired.Â </li>
<li>He wakes up early, not out of habit, but he just wakes up.Â </li>
<li>He lives so much in the present; he is so much in the present, he doesn't waste time. All time wasted is the time that isn't spent on the present, that isn't spent on what you are supposed to do now. Beast knows at each second what he is supposed to know. If not, he is restless and figures it out.Â </li>
<li>He has no fear of failing. He is indifferent to parries, people throwing stones at him.Â </li>
<li>He feels unstoppable. He can walk any path; he can make any path.Â </li>
</ol>
<p>Â </p>
<p><strong>Selling soul to the devil</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>He isn't touched, he isn't motivated, he doesn't need emotional stability. Even when he realises this, the devil pulls him in and asks him to get comfort without a soul.Â </li>
<li>For the fight of eternity, the beast feels the void sometimes; the pact with the devil makes him care less about the void, and get comfort in it.Â </li>
<li>So, sure, he won't have a social life. He won't let people in.</li>
<li>People would be restless, people would be scared, some would be worried. But the devil won't let him see this.</li>
<li>The devil will teach mediation as the suppression of emotions.Â </li>
<li>It is the comfort that the devil provides for the soul, so the beast doesn't have to look into his own soul. And the beast would like this, because - <strong>Ignorance, comfort from the pain of it.Â </strong></li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Selling soul to the bright, or the calmest Infinity</strong></p>
<ol>
<li>One who has everything, who has experienced every light and every darkness, selling soul to him, is still an exchange for the comfort. But his comfort is in accepting the light as it is, bright, dark - all are just variations.Â </li>
<li>He makes the beast feel pain, for the beast, even in pain, can keep moving. But interestingly, he would wait to check on others.Â </li>
<li>He makes the beast realise it isn't a race. He gives the beast time. He makes it apparent to the beast, it isn't a fight of eternity, but the beast himself isn't alone fighting.Â </li>
<li>Kids will still be inspired by the beast, soul with infinity will give others hope in the beast's eyes. He isn't scary anomre but equally potent.Â </li>
<li>And when the beast is alone, he sits beside him, he walks the roads with him.Â </li>
<li>Meditation, he teaches, is letting all emotions flow.Â </li>
<li>Acceptance - peace, calmness. This is what infinity would return for the soul. And once he realizes the beast is fully into the pact, He would just give the soul back.</li>
</ol>
<p>Â I made a few things abstract again. I am just learning to practice this. This is the first time I am writing about the above 3 entities and their relationships. I have a plan for the year, already written out somewhere. I have refined that to be more actionable and trackable. We will come back to evaluate and discuss them in an article of its own, maybe by the year's end ðŸ¤ž</p>
<p>It isn't 2020, it is 2025, and I have come a long way. âœŒ</p>
<p>Â </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Consistency</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/consistency.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/consistency.html</id>

        <updated>2025-08-31T20:10:44+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    What is it really?Â What does it mean to be consistent? What does it mean to be consistent with the routine? With the time, efforts, or results, what does consistency mean in day-to-day life? Does it mean doing x thing every day without missing out? Yes.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>What is it really?Â What does it mean to be consistent? What does it mean to be consistent with the routine? With the time, efforts, or results, what does consistency mean in day-to-day life?</p>
<p>Does it mean doing x thing every day without missing out? Yes. If you can do it every day. There are some extraordinary people who can do incredible things every day. Or some extremely consistent people can do the same thing every day, whatever, or however silly the repeating task is, the feat of doing the same thing every day is incredible. But for most people, everyday doesn't really mean "everyday".Â </p>
<p>There will be time, and always there will be time, in a loop, that you will miss out on a few days. With great things, great routine, new things you are trying, even when it is addictive, you will miss out on it one day. Consistency in life is defined by how quickly you can come back on track. You missed the routine yesterday. Can you be on it today? Two things -Â </p>
<ol>
<li>How fast can you realise you missed it</li>
<li>And how fast can you put yourself back on track</li>
</ol>
<p>Consistency and focus aren't a single long continuous line. They are actually one, one dashed line, where dashes and spaces between them are of different lengths. And the longer your dashes are, and the smaller your empty spaces are more consistent you are.Â </p>
<p>It is okay to miss out. Get back on track and keep hammering (Probably Shub owns the trademark for hammering). âš¡</p>
<p>Â </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Shall I do X for Y?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/internal-monologue-xyz.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/internal-monologue-xyz.html</id>

        <updated>2025-08-09T22:59:49+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I don't think anyone will understand this. If I share this with reference, maybe then it would make sense. For now, I am trying to make a decision. Should I do X for Y? Should I do when Y should be doing? Why should I&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I don't think anyone will understand this. If I share this with reference, maybe then it would make sense. For now, I am trying to make a decision.Â </p>
<p>Should I do X for Y? Should I do when Y should be doing? Why should I do?</p>
<p>Because I can, and I know Y should. But does Y want it? Does Y want it bad? I know you want it; I am sure if you want it badly. However, I am certain that X might be the best for Y.Â </p>
<p>How certain am I? There is nothing that can go wrong doing X. Is it? Well, most variables are under control. Give me numbers, I love numbers. We can't be accurate, but everything controllable can be controlled here. Let's say 80%. I would have said 90%, I am giving out 10% room for errors. More buffer. So, I am 80% certain Y will have a great time doing X. Concluded from the fact that Y has an 80% chance of making it.Â </p>
<p>Is 80% good enough to do something? If it were me, surely it is greater than 50%. So, in a very basic game of choice, it is a good choice. But there are more factors - Y is already doing Z, and Y only has n% of percentage will to do X.Â </p>
<p>Let's redo the math. In a basic choosing game, while choosing between two things or n things, you choose the one you want the most. One that makes the most sense to you. Each n has various factors. Here I am calculating - How much Y wants both choices. And I also have an option to play a part, influence this choice, why, and when I should intervene.Â </p>
<p>If I assume Z is constant, which is, in this case, because Y knows Z and I know Z and we agree on it being a constant. As in any case, Y loses the benefit of having Z. The Same benefit will always be there. Important variables are how much Y wants it. Yw, Delta of X, Xd.Â </p>
<p>So it's more of a question, how much better X is for Y, compared to Z. It is always better, number-wise, it is -</p>
<p>Xd <em> Yw = .8 </em>Â * (Yw)</p>
<p>If Y doesn't want it, then it is 0, if Y wants it 100%, then it is for sure 800% better. It is an 8x jump. No brainer to do it.Â </p>
<p>I should do this. And the question I shall ask here to Y is - Do you absolutely not want it?</p>
<p>Â <a href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/8020-time-to-negotiate.html">Combine this with a framework to make decisions for yourself</a> (pseudo math).Â </p>
<p>Â </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Reflections, mid 2025</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/reflections-2025.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/reflections-2025.html</id>

        <updated>2025-08-08T00:35:58+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    It is a reflection document. Not structured, unfiltered. Exactly 3 people said they would like to see my reflection notes last week, here I am. 12:12 am in the night, writing one (Friday, 8th August 2025). This is my approach to reflection that works for&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>It is a reflection document. Not structured, unfiltered. Exactly 3 people said they would like to see my reflection notes last week, here I am. 12:12 am in the night, writing one <strong>(Friday, 8th August 2025)</strong>. This is my approach to reflection that works for me. Have a read, see what strikes, feel free to try it out. Try it out for a few days, maybe copy this note to GPT, and do the reflection there. If you are new, it is much easier. If you want to get better, it is better to let your thoughts flow.Â </p>
<p><strong>Habit - Friday 8th, 2025</strong></p>
<p>It is 12:18 am, and I am writing this. I want to call out time here because it is way past my bedtime. I used to be in my bed by 11:30, 11:45 max. Well, 11:30 is the ideal one. I like waking up by 5.30 am. Gives me 6 hours, practically 5 hours of sleep. I used to take a few naps during the week, as I felt the need. I wake up late on Saturday, Sunday - 7/8 am.Â </p>
<p>This used to be so accurate, it was almost a habit. It was, because it hasn't anymore for the last few weeks. I am waking up same time, but sleeping late, by 12.10 am. That's almost 30 minutes late. Fortunately, it hasn't impacted my day. Still the same beast I am.Â </p>
<p>I slept at 2 am the day before, and worked till late. Woke up at 5 am, worked till 7.30 am, and got ready to go to a game. My parents were also heading to a medical checkup, and I was locking the house. I locked my room, kept my keys inside the parents' room, and locked the main door. I forgot something, so I unlocked the main door, got the keys from my parents' room, unlocked my room, got the stuff, locked my room, kept the key in my parents and locked the main door. I did this 3 times. Forgot - Phone charging cable first, Sunscreen 2nd, and the card key 3rd. While I was locking the room, I realised this isn't the best of me. Probably the worst of me. Thankfully, parents didn't notice. I can't be doing 3 round-trip flights at home. It was mainly because of a lack of sleep; I had taken a short 5-minute nap, and I was still sleepy and blanking out. Sleep is probably the biggest factor in lifestyle. There was a time for 2 years I was sleeping 4 hours and a few short naps in between; there are very successful people who do the same. 5 hours if I am getting regularly is good for me.Â </p>
<p>This started with a habit, and we are discussing bedtime. Bedtime is also a habit, right? Something you do so often that you don't have to think consciously of doing it. The body auto-tunes for the task. Our biological clock responds and optimises for the task because it has to do the same task, at the same time, or with the same trigger. Habits are good, they bring in structure, sometimes peak performance &amp; clarity. I am dead now, will write later.Â </p>
<p>Update: I slept at 12.40am. This is 10pm, Sat, Aug 9. tldr; I want to fix my bed time back to 11.30pm. You don't have a habit, you let your subconcious system take care of things, and by practice it must have gotten better.Â </p>
<p>So, two things I need to fixÂ </p>
<ol>
<li>Sleep at 11.30 pm</li>
<li>Wake up, open my door, and have some FaceTime with family early in the morning. I wake up early, max by 6 on weekdays, sometimes 8 on weekends, but my door usually opens around 8 every day. I don't know how many days I am at home, I would love to see these faces early in the morning, plus vitamin D.Â </li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Health</strong></p>
<p>I have been on a good track. Fair amount of physical activity. Mental-cognitive, logical, and creative, all parts firing. I haven't solved many math problems, but I managed to re-read a few chapters of the 11th book so far this year. ðŸ˜…</p>
<p>If anything health is a big tick. I need to start doing regular crunches again. I had a month long streak, and was feeling my abs. Have been acting lazy these days. I don't think any trigger, plain old lazzyness.Â </p>
<p><strong>Knowledge</strong></p>
<p>Read a few new books - Engineering leadership, Thinking in Bets - these are the highlights.Â </p>
<p>I started learning Sanskrit, can at least say - my name is Bikram. Not a lot of progress, need some more practice. But I take this as a done item for the first half.Â </p>
<p><strong>Wealth</strong></p>
<p>This is the only tracker I have failed to tick. I had a 40% exit, one highlight. I still have one 2x, but that's an old investment. Have mostly made foolish investments. I feel I don't give the attention money deserves post-earning. I need to get better at this, or do 10x my earnings ðŸ™ƒ or get someone to take care of my money. I am speaking like I have a lot of money ðŸ¤£. But I believe this attitude will bring the money. <a href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/faking-it-till-i-make-it.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fake it till you make it.Â </a></p>
<p><strong>How I feel</strong></p>
<p>I feel good. Positive, energetic, lighter, faster, calmer. I have gotten better in delegation, 2nd, and 3rd order thinking.Â  I don't think I am chasing any other feelings, emotions right now. It is a very healthy state.Â </p>
<p>Socially-emotionally, the last two quarters were the best. I found a lot of answers. Most importantly, what exactly do I need from a partner? I have met a few people. I should meet a few more. I am not a traditionalist, and I hate to admit, I am very specific. Randomly wired.Â </p>
<p><strong>Social Impact</strong></p>
<p>I have automated out of all socially active responsibilities. Instead of impacting masses, which I would love to do, can I ignite chain reactions? Can I find ways to play a part in people's lives who are going to have a great impact? Less investment of mine, faster results. And silent execution.Â </p>
<p><strong>What next?</strong></p>
<p>I figured it all out today, and was in the hospital with mom. Had some hours to think about this. But not exactly, looks like I will have to adjust the plan. Got more data points today. I will have 60% clarity for the next year, and will have the remaining 40% in the next 2 months. I can't share details. I don't have the details right now. Or I might have.Â </p>
<ul>
<li>It is either going to be a very fun cinematic time</li>
<li>Or very fun, hard grind</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>It is gonna be fun either way.Â </strong></p>
<p>The biggest realisation so far this year has been, I am good at making big statements. Not so good at breaking them down into steps.Â  If it is a problem, I do really well. If it is an idea, I am not so good. I need to do better. Starting with my 2025 goals, I have streamlined them into small trackable metrics. I can break them down and track them at the atomic level.Â </p>
<p>That's my mid-2025 recap.Â </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Men Don&#x27;t Cry</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/men-dont-cry.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/men-dont-cry.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/38/Screenshot-2025-08-05-at-11.46.07-AM.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2025-08-05T11:47:29+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/38/Screenshot-2025-08-05-at-11.46.07-AM.png" alt="Looking at void" />
                    Have you seen any man cry? Have you seen any man cry without getting drunk? Have you seen any man born before 2000 cry? If you have, you are close to them. Respect them, be there for them. Listen to them. Because usually men don't&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/38/Screenshot-2025-08-05-at-11.46.07-AM.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Looking at void" /></p>
                <p>Have you seen any man cry? Have you seen any man cry without getting drunk? Have you seen any man born before 2000 cry? If you have, you are close to them. Respect them, be there for them. Listen to them. Because usually men don't cry. Most of the time, men don't cry. In the hardest of times, men don't cry.Â </p>
<p>"Men don't cry" - It is an internet meme, used as a change-maker to encourage men to open up. To show the volatile self inside the hard shell. This article is also going to in the same topic. <strong>My personal experience of not crying and crying</strong>. Exposing the volatility out of my hard shell.Â </p>
<p>I grew up early, and I matured early compared to my mates. <strong>I acted like a man </strong>earlier than usual. Being a man in a traditional society like ours means being tough, <strong>being able to walk with a broken leg and not crying</strong>, not showing your weaknesses. This shapes the hollowness inside us. Not being able to talk out any volatility, the downs we are going through. Most of our fathers can be the brand ambassadors of this. They don't complain, they don't show pain, they don't cry. Maybe they do with a very, very close one. But they don't usually. We grow up watching the same, and we shape ourselves to the same. Being the eldest at home, I grew up even more like him. Not complaining a bit. Throw anything at me.Â </p>
<p>It was the end of 2011, and I had moved that year to Tezpur (a city close to my village) with a senior of mine. I was 15, he was 17. We were all by ourselves. We had a small room for ourselves, use had one bed, and some utensils to cook. From being pampered at home to being on our own. It was a big change. I knew all house chores, I bet I still can do them better than many, I bet I was better than almost all girls at that time. Our mom had health issues, and we started helping her from the 5th grade. Eventually, my younger brother did most of the chores, because that let him skip studies and get some appreciation, plus he loved me so much. He also had to take responsibility, because he was a man, maybe those chores gave him that feeling of being useful. I was used to all those chores, but home has a different feeling; the air you breathe feels different at home. Maybe it is just me. I was away from home for the first time. I was in a new school, and I didn't have anyone in my circle as I was different. I was trying hard.Â </p>
<p>One day, I came back home, mom was cooking chicken. I used to get special treatment. And the conversation started. To them, my life was chill; I didn't have to see the same rigor of home at that time. Life's daily needs were also occasionally hard. They were making sure I was doing well, they were making sure I could just focus on my studies and didn't have to know a lot that was going on at home. I cried out of nowhere. I cried out loud, told them how I was also finding that new life hard. New school, almost no friends, sometimes we used to cook once and eat for 2 days. I was kind of singled out at school because I didn't take tuition classes from the school teachers. And more importantly, I was missing my people, my brother, mom, and dad. And on top I there were these expectations on me, I wasn't sure if I was going to make it.Â </p>
<p>I have been the guy who could do it all, always. The world always seems to treat me specially, treating me easily. I wasn't used to the feeling I described above. Maybe that made me cry. I was out of my shell, exposing my volatility. That helped me so much in life. I am grateful I cried that day. That made my life easier. I felt lighter. I had so much built up, I had so much to tell, everything went out at once. Living that pure me. The child, the child I am till today. I still find it hard to expose my vulnerabilities, I have very less of those, the world has treated me nicely. I have wonderful people around me. But I can cry now. I can cry acting, I can cry watching an emotional, touching movie, I cry listening to a story, and more importantly, even though I find it hard to expose my vulnerabilities, not hard enough for them to build up and make me cry.</p>
<p>Men shouldn't cry because they build up so much. Men shouldn't cry because they have to be rough and tough always. Men should talk, have people around to listen to, and make sure they don't have to build up to cry one day. And if they build up somehow, let them cry. Be there, listen to them.Â </p>
<p>Shared this with a friend yesterday in response to Do I not feel lonely? My response was no. I don't. Above is the only time I felt lonely. I was surrounded by people, a school full of students, cricket coaching full of players, friends, and family, but I felt lonely because no one understood me. <strong>No one knew me because I didn't talk</strong>. I don't think there is anyone who understands me all in. And that's fine, I want to be a bit of mystery, even to this blog. It is fine, as long as my expectations of people knowing me are being fulfilled.Â </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Expectations, Reality, Happiness, and Peace</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/expectations-reality-happiness-and-peace.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/expectations-reality-happiness-and-peace.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/36/Screenshot-2025-07-27-at-7.44.07-PM.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2025-07-27T19:44:42+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/36/Screenshot-2025-07-27-at-7.44.07-PM.png" alt="Ladder to Another Place" />
                    Happiness is the difference between what we expect and what we experience. It is such a simple formula. A simple derivation is - lower the delta of expectations and reality, and be Happy. There are two ways to lower the delta 1 is easy. Or&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/36/Screenshot-2025-07-27-at-7.44.07-PM.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Ladder to Another Place" /></p>
                <p>Happiness is the difference between what we expect and what we experience. It is such a simple formula. A simple derivation is - lower the delta of expectations and reality, and be Happy.Â </p>
<p>There are two ways to lower the delta</p>
<ol>
<li>Lower your expectations</li>
<li>Improve your reality</li>
</ol>
<p>1 is easy. Or let's say, 1 is in your control theoretically. You are visiting a new place, meeting new people - lower what you expect. If things go well, you will be super happy. If not, you weren't expecting anything. We have experienced these kinds of experiences when we didn't have a lot of expectations, but reality treated us like the favourite child of god.Â  This is so easy, we have just solved the root of every grumpy face ever. Not yet. We want to get into the best university, we want to have the best food, we don't want to lower all our expectations, we can't always. Let's see if we can improve our reality.</p>
<p>We work hard, prepare our best, give our all, and yet do not get what we expect. Only if there was a secret mantra to get it all. There are so many factors; however hard we work, we don't control all. You put on your best dress and walk into an event on a sunny day, but suddenly, on the way, you are drenched in rain. It is too late to go back home to re-dress, it is too embarrassing to go to the event all wet. Life sucks. You do you improve this? Only if there were a secret mantra to fix the dress. If there were a secret mantra to control the weather. We don't have it yet, and we are doomed. As much as we think we are special, the chances of us being here are statistically -Infinity (Negative infinity). In that sense, we are special, still here. But our every expectation has a similar low chance of getting real. Irrespective of how hard we work. I know it doesn't help. But that's the reality.Â </p>
<p>Happiness is an illusion; reality is wild. Reality is a spectrum of joy, sorrow, anger, frustration, emptiness, profoundness, and whatnot. Accepting all is what being at peace is. This is the reality. And by accepting, we improve the reality. Not externally, but internally. We give our consciousness the space to flourish. Space to be the best of itself. Does this mean we accept and accept defeat? Yeah. We accept the current situation. And then, plan do we want to do next? Reflect and reset. And if we want to retry or go another route. Detach your motivation from emotions and results, and find joy in trying it well. There will be a time when you want something badly, it is fine to put everything, in fact, you should put everything, but you should know that at the same time, you don't control the results.Â  Krishna talks about this exact philosophy to Arjuna in the Gita.Â </p>
<ol>
<li>Accept your reality</li>
<li>Define your path</li>
<li>Walk the path with honesty</li>
<li>On every stop, loop back to 1</li>
<li>Remember, happiness is just a subset of what you are supposed to get. Be in peace.
<ol>
<li>Lowering expectations isn't the answer. Not when you care about reality.Â </li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>
<p><a href="https://www.productiveflourishing.com/p/users-guide-creative-tension" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer">There is a similar framework called creative tension</a>, which is similar but not exact, that talks about how you set high goals and keep everyone moving with the current reality from a leadership position. Thanks to Shubhankar.Â </p>
<p class="msg msg--info">Note: Originally written in 2022. Delivered a session in our poolside sessions at the Houseware retreat. We were sitting beside a pool, everyone had 30 minutes to talk about anything they wanted, and others could ask questions. I dropped - "Happiness is an illusion, and peace is all you need". Took everyone a while to recover ðŸ˜…</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>A new kind of thinking model</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/a-new-kind-of-thinking-model.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/a-new-kind-of-thinking-model.html</id>

        <updated>2025-07-24T21:57:16+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    It is going to be a little different. It is going to be new. It is the need of the hour; we either go extinct or evolve with the tools. I guess going extinct isn't an option, not in my world. Welcome evolution. This is&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>It is going to be a little different. It is going to be new. It is the need of the hour; we either go extinct or evolve with the tools. I guess going extinct isn't an option, not in my world. Welcome evolution. This is a living document/journal for the evolution.Â </p>
<p><strong>July 24th 2025</strong></p>
<p>I was in an interview, and my peers asked this question to the candidate: Given that I give you an open-ended problem, how would you spend the first 24 hours? What would you do? This is an interesting question and gives so much about how people think through problems, that's their framework for solving. Some of these pieces or the entire stack is changing fast in the AI-first world. I have been thinking about this for some time. Time to put a structure around it, maybe I am not yet ready to put a structure, but let's start brewing at least.Â </p>
<p>The candidate answered by saying - I would go do research, look at competitors, understand users, and would like to build a mind map around the problem. Mind map sounds so familiar, in fact, for everyone I hired, onboarded, I have given them initial space to go build their mind map and intuition of the space. I have personally done this myself so many times. It is hard to sell anything to me unless I am convinced to buy. I like to build my intuition on the product, whether I need to buy, similarly, what is the problem, why is it worth solving, and why now? Why us? What exactly does solving the problem mean? Building intuition and a mind map around connections. In the age of AI, what part of this can be delegated? What part of this is a good problem for AI? Building intuition is important, but it is also time-consuming &amp; biased towards my existing understanding/experience. And if AI works, what do I do with the free time? Do I start working on another idea? And come back once AI is done. My context switching needs to be better. As I would still like to build intuition, maybe better &amp; more efficient. How do I do this?Â </p>
<p><strong>July 27th 2025</strong></p>
<p>This is timely, as I have a few things to brainstorm, plan coming week. I should try to do them with tools and figure out how/where my mental model needs an upgrade. I have worked so much with these tools, and have even done a couple of conversation sentiment analyses. I don't know if anyone does this. But I had some hunches and wanted another opinion. The way I am looking at them right now is different.Â </p>
<p><strong>August 3rd 2025</strong></p>
<p>We have a hackathon this week, will have a lot of time to think about this. I shall make a lot of time to think about this.Â </p>
<p><strong>August 8th 2025</strong></p>
<p>I have mostly relied making changes on ai this week. Because I could afford, because I wanted to try.Â </p>
<ul>
<li>It has done good job at search. It has done good job at finding approaches.Â </li>
<li>It hasn't done a good job at implementation, it has still struggled with context. And with more ai writting these data, more diluated their data set will become for rich information.Â </li>
<li>Humans with expertise, rich information/skills will always bend ai to will, it will be just another tool.</li>
<li>No super agi, not in this architecture. Maybe not in this pricing.Â </li>
</ul>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Heist of the Century</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/the-heist-of-the-century.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/the-heist-of-the-century.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/34/Kid-In-Magician-Hat-Sitting-On-Pile-Of-Cash.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="life"/>

        <updated>2025-07-21T17:49:23+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/34/Kid-In-Magician-Hat-Sitting-On-Pile-Of-Cash.png" alt="" />
                    I searched for the term curious. Found a movie titled exactly "The heist of the century". I, too, pulled off a heist of a similar class. Well, of a similar amount ðŸ˜… I was in the 4th standard, and I don't remember all the details.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/34/Kid-In-Magician-Hat-Sitting-On-Pile-Of-Cash.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>I searched for the term curious. Found a movie titled exactly "The heist of the century". I, too, pulled off a heist of a similar class. Well, of a similar amount ðŸ˜…</p>
<p>I was in the 4th standard, and I don't remember all the details. I remember the highlights. And that's what I'm going to share here. I was never a problematic child at home. Never really needed an intervention, apart from - eat your food. It was one fine night, I made a pact with the devil, planned a heist of exactly 100 ruppees, and did a brilliant execution.Â </p>
<p>It was during the summer. My friends got into a fight over who could bring the most money to school. They could, but I was never dragged into those, as I was always everyone's favorite. Everyone wanted to share with me. But the fight this time around wasn't about eating, spending, or getting a share. It almost felt like a power game. Who has the biggest note? I had to pull myself into the game. I couldn't resist.Â </p>
<p>We wrapped dinner, and everyone went to bed. As I said, I don't remember the details; I might have been 7/8 years old. I woke up around 3.30 in the morning. Went to the stand where my father had hung his shirt. Got a stool to stand on, slipped my tinny hands into the pockets. Felt the biggest note, took a look, and there was just enough light from the rays coming through the bamboo ventilators, I was a 100 ruppees note. That was enough. No one could bring that big of a note. I put the stool back where it was earlier. Laid on the bed for 1 more hour, it was the season of mangos, and I used to visit my grandmother's house, 2 houses apart, every morning. Yes, I was her favourite always. My siblings and cousins often complain about how I was the favourite, I try to reason it, but in the case of my grandmother, yes, I was her favourite. So, I went there, hid the note in a bag of old clothes. We used to walk to school, 400 meters. I picked up the note on the way to school. Successful heist of the century.Â </p>
<p>If this were the end of the story, my story would have been different. Let me be more specific. During the midday break, the show started. Kids started pulling out 2, 5, and even 10 ruppes notes. I was laughing inside. Oh, poor kids, you don't know I could buy you all today. I pulled out my 100, and everyone was in awe. It must have been like them seeing god ðŸ˜†. Here is the twist: everything should have a twist ðŸ¤. On the way back from school, I said to all - Hey, let me have a treat for you all today. We went to a shop, the only shop open way back home. I remember the shopkeeper who used to adore me &amp; my brother. He said he didn't have the change. That was thoughtful. He was a wise and a man of full ethics. I don't find many people these days who wouldn't want a kid with money to spend all in their shop.Â </p>
<p>I came back from school, again, on the way back, went to grandma, and hid my money. I remember loving the possession of money; I think I was going to hold on to that note just forever, never spending. But no, whoever had written the script, the story was different. While I was hiding the money at Grandma's, one of my friends met our parents on the way and told them Bikram brought a huge note to school today. "Bikram le etro lamro hariyo note liyako thiyo aja school ma". I almost heard that when I entered home. I knew I got caught. I don't remember my brother being in school that day. If he were there, it couldn't have been this far, either. The next thing I remember was me rushing to Grandma, saving myself from a flying stick.Â </p>
<p>That early feeling of possession, that transition from free money to feeling it was my money, and holding onto it, and the power it made me feel, that stuck with me. For that, I remember saving enough to lend to my grandma and my father in my school days. And my grandma and parents used to return me with interest, I don't know if it was me figuring out the system or them teaching me savings, I like to believe it worked.Â Â </p>
<p class="msg msg--info">Originally written in 2021</p>
<p>Â </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
