<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Thebstar blogs</title>
    <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs" />
    <updated>2025-08-09T23:22:07+05:30</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Shall I do X for Y?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/internal-monologue-xyz.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/internal-monologue-xyz.html</id>

        <updated>2025-08-09T22:59:49+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    I don't think anyone will understand this. If I share this with reference, maybe then it would make sense. For now, I am trying to make a decision. Should I do X for Y? Should I do when Y should be doing? Why should I&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>I don't think anyone will understand this. If I share this with reference, maybe then it would make sense. For now, I am trying to make a decision. </p>
<p>Should I do X for Y? Should I do when Y should be doing? Why should I do?</p>
<p>Because I can, and I know Y should. But does Y want it? Does Y want it bad? I know you want it; I am sure if you want it badly. However, I am certain that X might be the best for Y. </p>
<p>How certain am I? There is nothing that can go wrong doing X. Is it? Well, most variables are under control. Give me numbers, I love numbers. We can't be accurate, but everything controllable can be controlled here. Let's say 80%. I would have said 90%, I am giving out 10% room for errors. More buffer. So, I am 80% certain Y will have a great time doing X. Concluded from the fact that Y has an 80% chance of making it. </p>
<p>Is 80% good enough to do something? If it were me, surely it is greater than 50%. So, in a very basic game of choice, it is a good choice. But there are more factors - Y is already doing Z, and Y only has n% of percentage will to do X. </p>
<p>Let's redo the math. In a basic choosing game, while choosing between two things or n things, you choose the one you want the most. One that makes the most sense to you. Each n has various factors. Here I am calculating - How much Y wants both choices. And I also have an option to play a part, influence this choice, why, and when I should intervene. </p>
<p>If I assume Z is constant, which is, in this case, because Y knows Z and I know Z and we agree on it being a constant. As in any case, Y loses the benefit of having Z. The Same benefit will always be there. Important variables are how much Y wants it. Yw, Delta of X, Xd. </p>
<p>So it's more of a question, how much better X is for Y, compared to Z. It is always better, number-wise, it is -</p>
<p>Xd <em> Yw = .8 </em> * (Yw)</p>
<p>If Y doesn't want it, then it is 0, if Y wants it 100%, then it is for sure 800% better. It is an 8x jump. No brainer to do it. </p>
<p>I should do this. And the question I shall ask here to Y is - Do you absolutely not want it? </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Reflections, mid 2025</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/reflections-2025.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/reflections-2025.html</id>

        <updated>2025-08-08T00:35:58+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    It is a reflection document. Not structured, unfiltered. Exactly 3 people said they would like to see my reflection notes last week, here I am. 12:12 am in the night, writing one (Friday, 8th August 2025). This is my approach to reflection that works for&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>It is a reflection document. Not structured, unfiltered. Exactly 3 people said they would like to see my reflection notes last week, here I am. 12:12 am in the night, writing one <strong>(Friday, 8th August 2025)</strong>. This is my approach to reflection that works for me. Have a read, see what strikes, feel free to try it out. Try it out for a few days, maybe copy this note to GPT, and do the reflection there. If you are new, it is much easier. If you want to get better, it is better to let your thoughts flow. </p>
<p><strong>Habit - Friday 8th, 2025</strong></p>
<p>It is 12:18 am, and I am writing this. I want to call out time here because it is way past my bedtime. I used to be in my bed by 11:30, 11:45 max. Well, 11:30 is the ideal one. I like waking up by 5.30 am. Gives me 6 hours, practically 5 hours of sleep. I used to take a few naps during the week, as I felt the need. I wake up late on Saturday, Sunday - 7/8 am. </p>
<p>This used to be so accurate, it was almost a habit. It was, because it hasn't anymore for the last few weeks. I am waking up same time, but sleeping late, by 12.10 am. That's almost 30 minutes late. Fortunately, it hasn't impacted my day. Still the same beast I am. </p>
<p>I slept at 2 am the day before, and worked till late. Woke up at 5 am, worked till 7.30 am, and got ready to go to a game. My parents were also heading to a medical checkup, and I was locking the house. I locked my room, kept my keys inside the parents' room, and locked the main door. I forgot something, so I unlocked the main door, got the keys from my parents' room, unlocked my room, got the stuff, locked my room, kept the key in my parents and locked the main door. I did this 3 times. Forgot - Phone charging cable first, Sunscreen 2nd, and the card key 3rd. While I was locking the room, I realised this isn't the best of me. Probably the worst of me. Thankfully, parents didn't notice. I can't be doing 3 round-trip flights at home. It was mainly because of a lack of sleep; I had taken a short 5-minute nap, and I was still sleepy and blanking out. Sleep is probably the biggest factor in lifestyle. There was a time for 2 years I was sleeping 4 hours and a few short naps in between; there are very successful people who do the same. 5 hours if I am getting regularly is good for me. </p>
<p>This started with a habit, and we are discussing bedtime. Bedtime is also a habit, right? Something you do so often that you don't have to think consciously of doing it. The body auto-tunes for the task. Our biological clock responds and optimises for the task because it has to do the same task, at the same time, or with the same trigger. Habits are good, they bring in structure, sometimes peak performance &amp; clarity. I am dead now, will write later. </p>
<p>Update: I slept at 12.40am. This is 10pm, Sat, Aug 9. tldr; I want to fix my bed time back to 11.30pm. You don't have a habit, you let your subconcious system take care of things, and by practice it must have gotten better. </p>
<p>So, two things I need to fix </p>
<ol>
<li>Sleep at 11.30 pm</li>
<li>Wake up, open my door, and have some FaceTime with family early in the morning. I wake up early, max by 6 on weekdays, sometimes 8 on weekends, but my door usually opens around 8 every day. I don't know how many days I am at home, I would love to see these faces early in the morning, plus vitamin D. </li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Health</strong></p>
<p>I have been on a good track. Fair amount of physical activity. Mental-cognitive, logical, and creative, all parts firing. I haven't solved many math problems, but I managed to re-read a few chapters of the 11th book so far this year. 😅</p>
<p>If anything health is a big tick. I need to start doing regular crunches again. I had a month long streak, and was feeling my abs. Have been acting lazy these days. I don't think any trigger, plain old lazzyness. </p>
<p><strong>Knowledge</strong></p>
<p>Read a few new books - Engineering leadership, Thinking in Bets - these are the highlights. </p>
<p>I started learning Sanskrit, can at least say - my name is Bikram. Not a lot of progress, need some more practice. But I take this as a done item for the first half. </p>
<p><strong>Wealth</strong></p>
<p>This is the only tracker I have failed to tick. I had a 40% exit, one highlight. I still have one 2x, but that's an old investment. Have mostly made foolish investments. I feel I don't give the attention money deserves post-earning. I need to get better at this, or do 10x my earnings 🙃 or get someone to take care of my money. I am speaking like I have a lot of money 🤣. But I believe this attitude will bring the money. Fake it till you make it. </p>
<p><strong>How I feel</strong></p>
<p>I feel good. Positive, energetic, lighter, faster, calmer. I have gotten better in delegation, 2nd, and 3rd order thinking.  I don't think I am chasing any other feelings, emotions right now. It is a very healthy state. </p>
<p>Socially-emotionally, the last two quarters were the best. I found a lot of answers. Most importantly, what exactly do I need from a partner? I have met a few people. I should meet a few more. I am not a traditionalist, and I hate to admit, I am very specific. Randomly wired. </p>
<p><strong>Social Impact</strong></p>
<p>I have automated out of all socially active responsibilities. Instead of impacting masses, which I would love to do, can I ignite chain reactions? Can I find ways to play a part in people's lives who are going to have a great impact? Less investment of mine, faster results. And silent execution. </p>
<p><strong>What next?</strong></p>
<p>I figured it all out today, was in the hospital with mom. Had some hours to think about this. But not exactly, looks like I will have to adjust the plan. Got more data points today. I will have 60% clarity for the next year, will have rest 40% in the next 2 months. I can't share details, I don't have the details right now. Or I might have. </p>
<ul>
<li>It is either going to be a very fun cinematic time</li>
<li>Or very fun, hard grind</li>
</ul>
<p>It is gonna be fun either way. That's my mid-2025 recap. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Men Don&#x27;t Cry</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/men-dont-cry.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/men-dont-cry.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/38/Screenshot-2025-08-05-at-11.46.07-AM.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2025-08-05T11:47:29+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/38/Screenshot-2025-08-05-at-11.46.07-AM.png" alt="Looking at void" />
                    Have you seen any man cry? Have you seen any man cry without getting drunk? Have you seen any man born before 2000 cry? If you have, you are close to them. Respect them, be there for them. Listen to them. Because usually men don't&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/38/Screenshot-2025-08-05-at-11.46.07-AM.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Looking at void" /></p>
                <p>Have you seen any man cry? Have you seen any man cry without getting drunk? Have you seen any man born before 2000 cry? If you have, you are close to them. Respect them, be there for them. Listen to them. Because usually men don't cry. Most of the time, men don't cry. In the hardest of times, men don't cry. </p>
<p>"Men don't cry" - It is an internet meme, used as a change-maker to encourage men to open up. To show the volatile self inside the hard shell. This article is also going to in the same topic. <strong>My personal experience of not crying and crying</strong>. Exposing the volatility out of my hard shell. </p>
<p>I grew up early, and I matured early compared to my mates. <strong>I acted like a man </strong>earlier than usual. Being a man in a traditional society like ours means being tough, <strong>being able to walk with a broken leg and not crying</strong>, not showing your weaknesses. This shapes the hollowness inside us. Not being able to talk out any volatility, the downs we are going through. Most of our fathers can be the brand ambassadors of this. They don't complain, they don't show pain, they don't cry. Maybe they do with a very, very close one. But they don't usually. We grow up watching the same, and we shape ourselves to the same. Being the eldest at home, I grew up even more like him. Not complaining a bit. Throw anything at me. </p>
<p>It was the end of 2011, and I had moved that year to Tezpur (a city close to my village) with a senior of mine. I was 15, he was 17. We were all by ourselves. We had a small room for ourselves, use had one bed, and some utensils to cook. From being pampered at home to being on our own. It was a big change. I knew all house chores, I bet I still can do them better than many, I bet I was better than almost all girls at that time. Our mom had health issues, and we started helping her from the 5th grade. Eventually, my younger brother did most of the chores, because that let him skip studies and get some appreciation, plus he loved me so much. He also had to take responsibility, because he was a man, maybe those chores gave him that feeling of being useful. I was used to all those chores, but home has a different feeling; the air you breathe feels different at home. Maybe it is just me. I was away from home for the first time. I was in a new school, and I didn't have anyone in my circle as I was different. I was trying hard. </p>
<p>One day, I came back home, mom was cooking chicken. I used to get special treatment. And the conversation started. To them, my life was chill; I didn't have to see the same rigor of home at that time. Life's daily needs were also occasionally hard. They were making sure I was doing well, they were making sure I could just focus on my studies and didn't have to know a lot that was going on at home. I cried out of nowhere. I cried out loud, told them how I was also finding that new life hard. New school, almost no friends, sometimes we used to cook once and eat for 2 days. I was kind of singled out at school because I didn't take tuition classes from the school teachers. And more importantly, I was missing my people, my brother, mom, and dad. And on top I there were these expectations on me, I wasn't sure if I was going to make it. </p>
<p>I have been the guy who could do it all, always. The world always seems to treat me specially, treating me easily. I wasn't used to the feeling I described above. Maybe that made me cry. I was out of my shell, exposing my volatility. That helped me so much in life. I am grateful I cried that day. That made my life easier. I felt lighter. I had so much built up, I had so much to tell, everything went out at once. Living that pure me. The child, the child I am till today. I still find it hard to expose my vulnerabilities, I have very less of those, the world has treated me nicely. I have wonderful people around me. But I can cry now. I can cry acting, I can cry watching an emotional, touching movie, I cry listening to a story, and more importantly, even though I find it hard to expose my vulnerabilities, not hard enough for them to build up and make me cry.</p>
<p>Men shouldn't cry because they build up so much. Men shouldn't cry because they have to be rough and tough always. Men should talk, have people around to listen to, and make sure they don't have to build up to cry one day. And if they build up somehow, let them cry. Be there, listen to them. </p>
<p>Shared this with a friend yesterday in response to Do I not feel lonely? My response was no. I don't. Above is the only time I felt lonely. I was surrounded by people, a school full of students, cricket coaching full of players, friends, and family, but I felt lonely because no one understood me. <strong>No one knew me because I didn't talk</strong>. I don't think there is anyone who understands me all in. And that's fine, I want to be a bit of mystery, even to this blog. It is fine, as long as my expectations of people knowing me are being fulfilled. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Expectations, Reality, Happiness, and Peace</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/expectations-reality-happiness-and-peace.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/expectations-reality-happiness-and-peace.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/36/Screenshot-2025-07-27-at-7.44.07-PM.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2025-07-27T19:44:42+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/36/Screenshot-2025-07-27-at-7.44.07-PM.png" alt="Ladder to Another Place" />
                    Happiness is the difference between what we expect and what we experience. It is such a simple formula. A simple derivation is - lower the delta of expectations and reality, and be Happy. There are two ways to lower the delta 1 is easy. Or&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/36/Screenshot-2025-07-27-at-7.44.07-PM.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Ladder to Another Place" /></p>
                <p>Happiness is the difference between what we expect and what we experience. It is such a simple formula. A simple derivation is - lower the delta of expectations and reality, and be Happy. </p>
<p>There are two ways to lower the delta</p>
<ol>
<li>Lower your expectations</li>
<li>Improve your reality</li>
</ol>
<p>1 is easy. Or let's say, 1 is in your control theoretically. You are visiting a new place, meeting new people - lower what you expect. If things go well, you will be super happy. If not, you weren't expecting anything. We have experienced these kinds of experiences when we didn't have a lot of expectations, but reality treated us like the favourite child of god.  This is so easy, we have just solved the root of every grumpy face ever. Not yet. We want to get into the best university, we want to have the best food, we don't want to lower all our expectations, we can't always. Let's see if we can improve our reality.</p>
<p>We work hard, prepare our best, give our all, and yet do not get what we expect. Only if there was a secret mantra to get it all. There are so many factors; however hard we work, we don't control all. You put on your best dress and walk into an event on a sunny day, but suddenly, on the way, you are drenched in rain. It is too late to go back home to re-dress, it is too embarrassing to go to the event all wet. Life sucks. You do you improve this? Only if there were a secret mantra to fix the dress. If there were a secret mantra to control the weather. We don't have it yet, and we are doomed. As much as we think we are special, the chances of us being here are statistically -Infinity (Negative infinity). In that sense, we are special, still here. But our every expectation has a similar low chance of getting real. Irrespective of how hard we work. I know it doesn't help. But that's the reality. </p>
<p>Happiness is an illusion; reality is wild. Reality is a spectrum of joy, sorrow, anger, frustration, emptiness, profoundness, and whatnot. Accepting all is what being at peace is. This is the reality. And by accepting, we improve the reality. Not externally, but internally. We give our consciousness the space to flourish. Space to be the best of itself. Does this mean we accept and accept defeat? Yeah. We accept the current situation. And then, plan do we want to do next? Reflect and reset. And if we want to retry or go another route. Detach your motivation from emotions and results, and find joy in trying it well. There will be a time when you want something badly, it is fine to put everything, in fact, you should put everything, but you should know that at the same time, you don't control the results.  Krishna talks about this exact philosophy to Arjuna in the Gita. </p>
<ol>
<li>Accept your reality</li>
<li>Define your path</li>
<li>Walk the path with honesty</li>
<li>On every stop, loop back to 1</li>
<li>Remember, happiness is just a subset of what you are supposed to get. Be in peace.
<ol>
<li>Lowering expectations isn't the answer. Not when you care about reality. </li>
</ol>
</li>
</ol>
<p><a href="https://www.productiveflourishing.com/p/users-guide-creative-tension" target="_blank" rel="nofollow noopener noreferrer">There is a similar framework called creative tension</a>, which is similar but not exact, that talks about how you set high goals and keep everyone moving with the current reality from a leadership position. Thanks to Shubhankar. </p>
<p class="msg msg--info">Note: Originally written in 2022. Delivered a session in our poolside sessions at the Houseware retreat. We were sitting beside a pool, everyone had 30 minutes to talk about anything they wanted, and others could ask questions. I dropped - "Happiness is an illusion, and peace is all you need". Took everyone a while to recover 😅</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>A new kind of thinking model</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/a-new-kind-of-thinking-model.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/a-new-kind-of-thinking-model.html</id>

        <updated>2025-07-24T21:57:16+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                    It is going to be a little different. It is going to be new. It is the need of the hour; we either go extinct or evolve with the tools. I guess going extinct isn't an option, not in my world. Welcome evolution. This is&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>It is going to be a little different. It is going to be new. It is the need of the hour; we either go extinct or evolve with the tools. I guess going extinct isn't an option, not in my world. Welcome evolution. This is a living document/journal for the evolution. </p>
<p><strong>July 24th 2025</strong></p>
<p>I was in an interview, and my peers asked this question to the candidate: Given that I give you an open-ended problem, how would you spend the first 24 hours? What would you do? This is an interesting question and gives so much about how people think through problems, that's their framework for solving. Some of these pieces or the entire stack is changing fast in the AI-first world. I have been thinking about this for some time. Time to put a structure around it, maybe I am not yet ready to put a structure, but let's start brewing at least. </p>
<p>The candidate answered by saying - I would go do research, look at competitors, understand users, and would like to build a mind map around the problem. Mind map sounds so familiar, in fact, for everyone I hired, onboarded, I have given them initial space to go build their mind map and intuition of the space. I have personally done this myself so many times. It is hard to sell anything to me unless I am convinced to buy. I like to build my intuition on the product, whether I need to buy, similarly, what is the problem, why is it worth solving, and why now? Why us? What exactly does solving the problem mean? Building intuition and a mind map around connections. In the age of AI, what part of this can be delegated? What part of this is a good problem for AI? Building intuition is important, but it is also time-consuming &amp; biased towards my existing understanding/experience. And if AI works, what do I do with the free time? Do I start working on another idea? And come back once AI is done. My context switching needs to be better. As I would still like to build intuition, maybe better &amp; more efficient. How do I do this? </p>
<p><strong>July 27th 2025</strong></p>
<p>This is timely, as I have a few things to brainstorm, plan coming week. I should try to do them with tools and figure out how/where my mental model needs an upgrade. I have worked so much with these tools, and have even done a couple of conversation sentiment analyses. I don't know if anyone does this. But I had some hunches and wanted another opinion. The way I am looking at them right now is different. </p>
<p><strong>August 3rd 2025</strong></p>
<p>We have a hackathon this week, will have a lot of time to think about this. I shall make a lot of time to think about this. </p>
<p><strong>August 8th 2025</strong></p>
<p>I have mostly relied making changes on ai this week. Because I could afford, because I wanted to try. </p>
<ul>
<li>It has done good job at search. It has done good job at finding approaches. </li>
<li>It hasn't done a good job at implementation, it has still struggled with context. And with more ai writting these data, more diluated their data set will become for rich information. </li>
<li>Humans with expertise, rich information/skills will always bend ai to will, it will be just another tool.</li>
<li>No super agi, not in this architecture. Maybe not in this pricing. </li>
</ul>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Heist of the Century</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/the-heist-of-the-century.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/the-heist-of-the-century.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/34/Kid-In-Magician-Hat-Sitting-On-Pile-Of-Cash.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="life"/>

        <updated>2025-07-21T17:49:23+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/34/Kid-In-Magician-Hat-Sitting-On-Pile-Of-Cash.png" alt="" />
                    I searched for the term curious. Found a movie titled exactly "The heist of the century". I, too, pulled off a heist of a similar class. Well, of a similar amount 😅 I was in the 4th standard, and I don't remember all the details.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/34/Kid-In-Magician-Hat-Sitting-On-Pile-Of-Cash.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>I searched for the term curious. Found a movie titled exactly "The heist of the century". I, too, pulled off a heist of a similar class. Well, of a similar amount 😅</p>
<p>I was in the 4th standard, and I don't remember all the details. I remember the highlights. And that's what I'm going to share here. I was never a problematic child at home. Never really needed an intervention, apart from - eat your food. It was one fine night, I made a pact with the devil, planned a heist of exactly 100 ruppees, and did a brilliant execution. </p>
<p>It was during the summer. My friends got into a fight over who could bring the most money to school. They could, but I was never dragged into those, as I was always everyone's favorite. Everyone wanted to share with me. But the fight this time around wasn't about eating, spending, or getting a share. It almost felt like a power game. Who has the biggest note? I had to pull myself into the game. I couldn't resist. </p>
<p>We wrapped dinner, and everyone went to bed. As I said, I don't remember the details; I might have been 7/8 years old. I woke up around 3.30 in the morning. Went to the stand where my father had hung his shirt. Got a stool to stand on, slipped my tinny hands into the pockets. Felt the biggest note, took a look, and there was just enough light from the rays coming through the bamboo ventilators, I was a 100 ruppees note. That was enough. No one could bring that big of a note. I put the stool back where it was earlier. Laid on the bed for 1 more hour, it was the season of mangos, and I used to visit my grandmother's house, 2 houses apart, every morning. Yes, I was her favourite always. My siblings and cousins often complain about how I was the favourite, I try to reason it, but in the case of my grandmother, yes, I was her favourite. So, I went there, hid the note in a bag of old clothes. We used to walk to school, 400 meters. I picked up the note on the way to school. Successful heist of the century. </p>
<p>If this were the end of the story, my story would have been different. Let me be more specific. During the midday break, the show started. Kids started pulling out 2, 5, and even 10 ruppes notes. I was laughing inside. Oh, poor kids, you don't know I could buy you all today. I pulled out my 100, and everyone was in awe. It must have been like them seeing god 😆. Here is the twist: everything should have a twist 🤐. On the way back from school, I said to all - Hey, let me have a treat for you all today. We went to a shop, the only shop open way back home. I remember the shopkeeper who used to adore me &amp; my brother. He said he didn't have the change. That was thoughtful. He was a wise and a man of full ethics. I don't find many people these days who wouldn't want a kid with money to spend all in their shop. </p>
<p>I came back from school, again, on the way back, went to grandma, and hid my money. I remember loving the possession of money; I think I was going to hold on to that note just forever, never spending. But no, whoever had written the script, the story was different. While I was hiding the money at Grandma's, one of my friends met our parents on the way and told them Bikram brought a huge note to school today. "Bikram le etro lamro hariyo note liyako thiyo aja school ma". I almost heard that when I entered home. I knew I got caught. I don't remember my brother being in school that day. If he were there, it couldn't have been this far, either. The next thing I remember was me rushing to Grandma, saving myself from a flying stick. </p>
<p>That early feeling of possession, that transition from free money to feeling it was my money, and holding onto it, and the power it made me feel, that stuck with me. For that, I remember saving enough to lend to my grandma and my father in my school days. And my grandma and parents used to return me with interest, I don't know if it was me figuring out the system or them teaching me savings, I like to believe it worked.  </p>
<p class="msg msg--info">Originally written in 2021</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Crush</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/the-crush.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/the-crush.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/33/Screenshot-2025-07-20-at-8.23.21-AM.png" medium="image" />

        <updated>2025-07-20T01:07:54+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/33/Screenshot-2025-07-20-at-8.23.21-AM.png" alt="" />
                    I had a crush 🥰. I had shared this on my WhatsApp 2 years ago. I was talking to a friend a few days ago. I shared a song. And shared how it feels. I also shared that I had a crush. It was a&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/33/Screenshot-2025-07-20-at-8.23.21-AM.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>I had a crush 🥰. I had shared this on my WhatsApp 2 years ago. I was talking to a friend a few days ago. I shared a song. And shared how it feels. I also shared that I had a crush. It was a long, long time ago - Way back in school. </p>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/33/Screenshot-2025-07-20-at-12.17.32-AM.png" alt="" width="1488" height="206" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/33/responsive/Screenshot-2025-07-20-at-12.17.32-AM-xs.png 640w ,https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/33/responsive/Screenshot-2025-07-20-at-12.17.32-AM-sm.png 768w ,https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/33/responsive/Screenshot-2025-07-20-at-12.17.32-AM-md.png 1024w ,https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/33/responsive/Screenshot-2025-07-20-at-12.17.32-AM-lg.png 1366w ,https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/33/responsive/Screenshot-2025-07-20-at-12.17.32-AM-xl.png 1600w ,https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/33/responsive/Screenshot-2025-07-20-at-12.17.32-AM-2xl.png 1920w"></figure>
<p>This is exactly what I mean by Crush. No, it isn't a typo for Crash, which I also had a few years ago. The front bonnet of the car I was driving was destroyed. Thankfully, I wasn't even hurt. Changed me to realise small joys even more &amp; drive more carefully. Well, that's a different story. A blissful evening all by myself is better spent structuring my Crush story. </p>
<h3>My heart dropped a beat</h3>
<figure class="post__image"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/33/Screenshot-2025-07-20-at-12.29.39-AM.png" alt="" width="620" height="527" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" srcset="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/33/responsive/Screenshot-2025-07-20-at-12.29.39-AM-xs.png 640w ,https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/33/responsive/Screenshot-2025-07-20-at-12.29.39-AM-sm.png 768w ,https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/33/responsive/Screenshot-2025-07-20-at-12.29.39-AM-md.png 1024w ,https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/33/responsive/Screenshot-2025-07-20-at-12.29.39-AM-lg.png 1366w ,https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/33/responsive/Screenshot-2025-07-20-at-12.29.39-AM-xl.png 1600w ,https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/33/responsive/Screenshot-2025-07-20-at-12.29.39-AM-2xl.png 1920w">     </figure>
<p>I was at a wedding, sitting beside a beautiful lady, married. She asked me -</p>
<p>She - When are you getting married?</p>
<p>Me - I don't know</p>
<p><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">She - Why?</span></p>
<p>Me - Because I haven't found anyone compatible.</p>
<p>I didn't want to make it a long answer. I didn't want to tell her a lot, explain what I was thinking. We weren't that connected. We were in a wedding venue, and had to scream every time to be audible. I thought we could move on from the conversation with this answer. She asked</p>
<p><span style="color: var(--text-primary-color); font-family: var(--editor-font-family); font-size: inherit; font-weight: var(--font-weight-normal);">She - How? Why did you not set someone up?</span></p>
<p>She giggled and went on to mention how everyone is doing love marriage, and not seeing someone is a bad idea. </p>
<p>Oh, boy, for a second my heart dropped a beat. For a second, I wanted to tell her - <strong>because I HAD A CRUSH ON YOU. It was a long time back, but it was special</strong>.</p>
<p>It would have been a scene. I don't mind paying for such a scene. You know the saying, Thoughts travel faster than light. It did, and it did ruin the scene. I didn't tell her anything. I laughed, agreed, and moved on. In an alternate universe, I would have screamed for sure. </p>
<p> </p>
<h3>How beautiful she is <span style="text-decoration: line-through;">(was)</span></h3>
<p>She was really beautiful. And beauty is all in the eyes; it depends on who is looking and what they are looking at. I am not gonna give specifics for you people to figure this out. And if you feel like the girl, no, you weren't. Even when we had the above conversation. I had similar conversations with a lot of you in a very similar setup. What else do we have in common to talk otherwise? Maybe that was you. Keep reading. You had a great impact.</p>
<p>I had a crush on her. She was really beautiful. She had beautiful eyes. She was caring and full of optimism. She was so perfect. Felt my heart was beating for her - <a href="https://youtu.be/iasxMdSu7Jo?si=7h__RoE6Yog1wHig">jiya dhadak, dhadak jaye (Youtube link)</a>. This was the song I had shared with my friend. </p>
<p>The crush lasted for maybe 2/3 months. I never told her. I am the opposite of an impulse doer. In people I used to observe and observe. For things I used to procrastinate, this is my trick to stay under my budget. I was observing her - she gave me hope every day. She. gave me optimism every day. We didn't talk about these things - ever. But she did give me all the energy I needed at that time. Optimism was all I needed at that time. </p>
<p>After 2/3 months, the crush faded away. Seeing her again never gave me the same blush. I used to have high expectations from people - on parameters like honesty, keeping a lot of self-pride, being specific and conscious about ownself. She wasn't there in many of those parameters, I realised. I still felt special, I still felt in love, but a picture of her faded in my heart.</p>
<p>She taught me love, well, she doesn't know she taught me. She taught me the purest form of love. I used to walk on the field (Barikhar Khetir Ali) in monsoon rain, to help father in farming, I used to write songs, and I started writing poems. A heavy rain still takes me back to that feeling. I wasn't in love with her anymore; <strong>I started loving the feeling of love </strong>instead. I used to go for a run, and I thought someone was watching. This used to make me feel special; it still does. I used to write thinking someone was reading, and I still do. I am still blushing. Optimism that feeling gave me, I felt special, every time I fell, that feeling was there to pick me up.</p>
<p>I have never described this. I don't know how to describe. I feel I can write a poem, and that will explain this better. That feeling made me cheer the monsoon rain, sing blue sky, and clouds; that feeling helped me be where I am. I am not an artist, not a school-trained traditional one, but still, that feeling made me one. Or so I like to believe. </p>
<p> </p>
<h3>The gift of love</h3>
<p>As I said, her picture has faded, and I don't even remember well how she looked back then. I tried one day remembering her very hard in the middle of a reflection time, plus rain. No, I couldn't remember her face. But this feeling is eternal. This feeling of love, of being special - this is going to last with me forever. This gives me optimism, as it was a big part of the hopes I had. It is a big part of the peace I have. It is so pure, I look at parents and find the same kind of love. It is all about giving and not expecting anything in return. But it gives so much back. I have seen fathers giving up their drinking habit, and I have seen mothers becoming stronger, more resilient, confident, and independent. Love without expectations, without anything in return, does return so much more than people with expectations can ever imagine. </p>
<p>Leaving you here with a movie that reflects a similar journey. It is a good watch and completes what I am saying here. </p>
<p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FE0ZLvfITSc" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Nanhe Jaisalmer - Youtube link</a><br><br></p>
<p class="msg msg--highlight ">Note: I didn't add details about her, no specific timelines, no specific places. I know a few people with a lot of time interested in figuring this out. I can't leave clues here. But if we had the above conversation, you would know it was you. You had a big impact, without realizing it. </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Parents - The hardest-working labour class</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/parents-the-hardest-working-labour-class.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/parents-the-hardest-working-labour-class.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/32/Screenshot-2025-07-12-at-10.27.06-PM.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="life"/>

        <updated>2025-07-12T22:27:46+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/32/Screenshot-2025-07-12-at-10.27.06-PM.png" alt="Farmer is back home at dusk tim" />
                    Parents are the hardest-working labour class people in the world. It was summer, and I had just finished my 6th-grade half-yearly exams. All I could think about was a blissful 30-day vacation filled with cricket. But one pivotal afternoon, my plans unexpectedly changed, leading me&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/32/Screenshot-2025-07-12-at-10.27.06-PM.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Farmer is back home at dusk tim" /></p>
                <div class="xdj266r x14z9mp xat24cr x1lziwak x1vvkbs x126k92a">
<div dir="auto">Parents are the hardest-working labour class people in the world.</div>
<div dir="auto"> </div>
</div>
<div class="x14z9mp xat24cr x1lziwak x1vvkbs xtlvy1s x126k92a">
<div dir="auto">It was summer, and I had just finished my 6th-grade half-yearly exams. All I could think about was a blissful 30-day vacation filled with cricket. But one pivotal afternoon, my plans unexpectedly changed, leading me to discover a deep respect for the hardest-working people I know: my parents.</div>
<div dir="auto"> </div>
</div>
<div class="x14z9mp xat24cr x1lziwak x1vvkbs xtlvy1s x126k92a">
<div dir="auto">It <a class="html-a xdj266r x14z9mp xat24cr x1lziwak xexx8yu xyri2b x18d9i69 x1c1uobl x1hl2dhg x16tdsg8 x1vvkbs" tabindex="-1"></a>was just past 2 PM, and I was ready for a day of play after lunch. First, I needed to get a jar of water to my dad, who was working under the scorching sun on an MGNREGA project, just 800 meters from our house. I raced over, handed him the jar, and was about to head back when he asked me to fill in for him for just 15 minutes while he fed the cows.</div>
<div dir="auto"> </div>
</div>
<div class="x14z9mp xat24cr x1lziwak x1vvkbs xtlvy1s x126k92a">
<div dir="auto">I agreed, although I managed to negotiate it down from the 30 minutes he originally asked for. There I was, shovel in hand, helping to dig a pool. I was annoyed at missing out on time with my friends. Minutes turned into hours, stretching unexpectedly until 4 PM. We were done for the day.</div>
<div dir="auto"> </div>
</div>
<div class="x14z9mp xat24cr x1lziwak x1vvkbs xtlvy1s x126k92a">
<div dir="auto">Walking home, I was furious. I felt tricked and disappointed. I couldn’t even look at my dad when I saw him still working on our farm. In a burst of anger, I threw the water jar aside and vented all my frustrations. That night was restless, filled with rage and tears.</div>
</div>
<div class="x14z9mp xat24cr x1lziwak x1vvkbs xtlvy1s x126k92a">
<div dir="auto">The next morning, with my anger slightly gone, I decided to go back to work. Maybe part of me wanted to make him feel guilty.</div>
<div dir="auto"> </div>
<div dir="auto">I worked the entire day and realized just how much my father did for us. Even the previous day, while I was at the pool, he was still working on the farm. The work at the pool was relatively easier, and there were many others like him, working hard for their families, some only a few years older than me. I realized it was an opportunity to help the hardest-working person I knew. I could still play after 4 PM. I returned home that day and decided to continue working with a smile. For the next 20 days, I worked not out of obligation, but out of deep respect and joy in sharing these burdens.</div>
<div dir="auto"> </div>
</div>
<div class="x14z9mp xat24cr x1lziwak x1vvkbs xtlvy1s x126k92a">
<div dir="auto">Each day revealed more about my parents' daily sacrifices, showing the depth of their commitment and love. Those days deepened my respect and love for them. I understood just how much they did for us. Every drop of sweat, every decision, every sacrifice was clear, maybe I still can't comprehend everything.</div>
<div dir="auto"> </div>
<div dir="auto">The sweet moments felt sweeter, and the hard times seemed easier. They could no longer trick me with claims like - they enjoyed grinding in the sun, or they disliked our favorite sabji so we siblings could eat more, or they preferred hard food so we could enjoy the tender parts. </div>
<div dir="auto"> </div>
<div dir="auto">Note: Converted from my phone notes. Had published on FB a long time ago. </div>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The Playlist</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/the-playlist.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/the-playlist.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/31/Screenshot-2025-07-11-at-7.40.27-AM.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="life"/>

        <updated>2025-07-11T07:41:18+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/31/Screenshot-2025-07-11-at-7.40.27-AM.png" alt="Musical notes" />
                    A friend sent me her playlist today. I had asked for it, and it made me think: if life were like a Spotify playlist. If you could pick only songs you like, and play them on loop. If you could select people, select moments, and&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/31/Screenshot-2025-07-11-at-7.40.27-AM.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Musical notes" /></p>
                <p>A friend sent me her playlist today. I had asked for it, and it made me think: if life were like a Spotify playlist. If you could pick only songs you like, and play them on loop. If you could select people, select moments, and put them on a playlist, and if you could replay some of them. </p>
<p>I don't feel like writing more. I have pretty much said everything I wanted to say above, and I will add just a few more lines. Indeed, life is like a playlist - you can almost always choose people you want to be friends with, people you want to work with, and you can even tune people at times to what you want them in your playlist to be. Okay, life is more like a free Spotify account. You get to build a playlist, but you have to try songs, artists, and in the process, sometimes it is fine to not like some. Put the best in your playlist. Doesn't mean the song is bad. Someone put their soul into it. Some billion people listened to it. Somehow, after a week, you are in a different mode, and suddenly you like the song. Life changes right!</p>
<p>Life changes, so do our choices. They change themselves, and they change others too. I said free Spotify, do you recall? Free Spotify comes with unavoidable ads, the sorrows of life. You don't like it, but you can't skip. Hold yourself together, it will pass. It always passes. </p>
<p>Try more, add more songs, or just play the recommended one. If you feel adventurous, try a new genre. Do it your way; it is your playlist. Remember one thing, the joy of having a playlist is in playing it, listening to it. </p>
<p>Enjoy your playlist, I am enjoying the one shared with me. It is playing. 🎼</p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>The ego of a conversation</title>
        <author>
            <name>Bikram Sutar</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/the-ego-of-a-conversation.html"/>
        <id>https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/the-ego-of-a-conversation.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/30/Screenshot-2025-07-10-at-1.49.01-AM.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="life"/>
            <category term="fokat"/>

        <updated>2025-07-10T01:50:06+05:30</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/30/Screenshot-2025-07-10-at-1.49.01-AM.png" alt="Doctor Strange (2016)" />
                    Have you watched Doctor Strange (2016) (YouTube link)? If you haven't already, do watch before reading further. Click on the link above. It is just a 2-minute scene in 2x. Great. In the scene, Strange traps Dormammu in a time loop. Strange keeps coming back,&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://www.thebstar.com/blogs/media/posts/30/Screenshot-2025-07-10-at-1.49.01-AM.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="Doctor Strange (2016)" /></p>
                <p data-start="1300" data-end="1333"><a href="https://youtu.be/LrHTR22pIhw?si=I5Ezz3d6AKlnzVvL" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Have you watched <strong>Doctor Strange (2016) (YouTube link)</strong></a>?<br data-start="1372" data-end="1375">If you haven't already, do watch before reading further. Click on the link above. It is just a 2-minute scene in 2x.</p>
<p data-start="1300" data-end="1333">Great. In the scene, Strange traps Dormammu in a time loop. Strange keeps coming back, again and again, repeating the same thing while Dormammu gets increasingly frustrated. You watched it right 🙄</p>
<p data-start="1553" data-end="1697">On paper, it’s a one-sided conversation. But <strong data-start="1619" data-end="1659">that conversation has enormous value</strong>. It decides the fate of the universe. And if my conversations were of that magnitude, I’d also show up endlessly. No hesitation. No fatigue. No complaints.</p>
<p data-start="1819" data-end="1897">But most conversations aren’t Dormammu deals.</p>
<h3 data-start="1904" data-end="1929"><a href="https://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/english/ego" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ego</a> - Red vs Green</h3>
<ol>
<li><span style="color: #2dc26b;"><strong>Green ego</strong> - Your idea or opinion of yourself, your feeling of your importance, and your ability</span></li>
<li><span style="color: #e03e2d;"><strong>Red ego</strong> - Hidden, unspoken desires, resulting in real-world demand</span></li>
</ol>
<p data-start="1931" data-end="2034">Dormammu, in that scene, is all <span style="color: #e03e2d;"><strong data-start="1963" data-end="1974">Red Ego</strong></span>.<br data-start="1975" data-end="1978">He’s demanding outcomes, submission, his way or nothing.</p>
<p data-start="2036" data-end="2239">Strange, on the other hand, carries a <strong data-start="2074" data-end="2087"><span style="color: #2dc26b;">Green Ego</span> </strong>- a healthy, maybe a bit overconfident awareness of his worth. He knows what he’s capable of. He knows why he matters. He knows what the stakes are. And that’s why he can endure the loop.</p>
<p data-start="2036" data-end="2239">He’s not chasing Dormammu’s validation. He’s protecting the world. Doing his duty. That's the conversation.</p>
<h3 data-start="2357" data-end="2388">My green ego</h3>
<p data-start="2390" data-end="2532">I try to protect my <span style="color: #2dc26b;"><strong data-start="2427" data-end="2440">Green Ego</strong></span> in a conversation.<br data-start="2448" data-end="2451">I know why I am in it.  And frankly, I’m overconfident about it. Hence, I won't ever pull out the awkwardness trick. Awkwardness in these situations is real. But think deeply, and awkwardness is nothing but an illusion for underconfidence or a conversation not having a green ego. </p>
<p data-start="2534" data-end="2734"><strong data-start="2534" data-end="2572">Yes, each conversation should have an ego</strong><br data-start="2572" data-end="2575">A healthy, <span style="color: #2dc26b;"><strong data-start="2586" data-end="2599">Green Ego</strong></span> in a conversation means it sustains itself.<br data-start="2643" data-end="2646">People feel its value, the importance. Everyone wants to return. It has dignity. It has momentum.</p>
<p data-start="2736" data-end="2913">When a conversation lacks that when it’s one-sided, when it needs to be dragged, my Green Ego reminds me I’m not stuck in a time loop. And unless I am dealing with Dormammu, I should not create the loop. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
